<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>nodnod.net</title>
<description>nodnod.net by David Zhou</description>
<atom:link href="http://nodnod.net/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<link>http://nodnod.net/</link>
<language>en-us</language>

<item>
<title>A Novice&#39;s Thoughts on the Valve Hardware Announcement</title>
<author>username@siteurl.com (Site Author)</author>
<link>http://nodnod.net/2025/11/26/Valve-Hardware-Announcement.html</link>
<guid>http://nodnod.net/2025/11/26/Valve-Hardware-Announcement.html</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500GMT</pubDate>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;Valve announced 3 new pieces of hardware, the Stream Controller, Steam Machine, and Steam Frame. Each piece of hardware is a powerful device serving it&#39;s own purpose with all of them working together seamlessly effectively giving steam their own ecosystem to rule over gaming. The steam controller is feature packed even more so than Sony&#39;s DualSense controller, featuring next-generation magnetic TMR -Tunneling Magnetoresistance- giving the best accuracy with zero dead zone and drift, four haptic motors, and capacitive touch all while keeping the beloved touchpads from the Steam Deck. The Steam Machine is a powerful small form factor Linux PC optimized for gaming in the low to medium graphics range, with the ability to open it up to add storage or even upgrade your system ram. Last but far from least the impressive Steam Frame, a standalone VR headset with full access to your steam library, borderline futuristic game streaming, and controllers that bare zero resemblance to their competition. Next year will be a strong one for Valve and could be revolutionary for the gaming hardware industry. All of this without mentioning AI once, good job Valve. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Steam Controller is by far my most anticipated device after a certain statement about the Steam Machine that I will cover later, I&#39;m a huge fan of the customizability of the Steam Deck&#39;s controllers and making them useable in any game even ones that don&#39;t support controllers natively, and as I&#39;ve grown to enjoy playing games with a controller more and more it would be really nice having a Steam Deck like controller without it being a whole computer and costing $400+. Now for it&#39;s full feature list, 4 rumble motors total, two LRA haptic motors in the trackpads, and two High output LRA haptic motors for rumble. This should offer high dynamic haptic feedback especially for the trackpads making them feel much more responsive than if they didn&#39;t have it. The trackpads themselves aren&#39;t much better, though they are 2mm larger. The controller still has the four back buttons, a 6-axis IMU -Inertial Measurement Unit- for gyro controllers, and a new feature capacitive touch in the controller grip allowing for you to set actions to them with Valve&#39;s example being to hold and release to enable gyro aim, I&#39;m not sure how well it&#39;ll work and how sensitive it is but we&#39;ll see when people get to play with it more. The last exciting feature for the controller is it&#39;s connectivity, it supports Bluetooth and wired like most controllers but also comes with a 2.4GHz wireless dongle. This allows easy pairing where you just plug it into a USB and use it, it also allows you to charge the controller using 3 pogo-pins and each puck can support up to 4 controllers being paired at once. the 2.4GHz connection achieves a claimed 8ms end-to-end latency. This should be a powerful contender with other high end controllers for gaming on PC. It is unclear now if this dongle will work on consoles like the 8BitDo but I highly doubt it. Overall I&#39;m excited for the release of this controller, with it being higher end I do fear the price but I&#39;m sure whatever the price may be it will be worth it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Steam Machine is Valve&#39;s jump into the console market. They had history in the past with the first Steam Machine but it wasn&#39;t much of a success and it was on a much much older version of SteamOS. Now steam has experience working and SteamOS has grown much bigger thanks to the success of the Steam Deck. The Steam Machine is a small form factor PC and when they call it small form factor they mean it with it being a 6-inch cube. It running SteamOS 3 with all the features you are used to from the Steam Deck but this time it&#39;s meant to sit in one place and can be used from your couch for some console style gaming or at a desk with a keyboard and mouse letting you use it like a standard desktop PC. The Steam Machine is very tall for a system like itself so what is the height used for? Unlike a desktop system it doesn&#39;t need a huge GPU so they are able to commit that space all to the cooling, with a large percentage of it&#39;s vertical footprint being a heatsink and a large fan to blow air out the back of the system. This should help keep thermals well under control and we&#39;ll likely see that put to the test once reviewers can get their hands on this hardware and can test it. Despite it&#39;s size though it&#39;s I/O is impressive, on the front there are 2 USB-A 3.2 Gen 1 ports and a high speed microSD card slot allowing you to take the microSD card out of your Steam Deck and plug it straight into the Steam Machine to have all of your games on the move. On the back of the Machine there are 2 USB-A 2.0 ports, 1 USB-C 3.2 Gen 2, a Gigabit ethernet port, an AC power connector, HDMI 2.0 I&#39;ll cover this in more detail in a second, and DisplayPort 1.4. Overall a powerful I/O lineup except for HDMI 2.0 so what&#39;s up with that, well HDMI unlike DisplayPort -which is open-source- is a licensed connector that has lots of regulation, but that&#39;s where it gets confusing when looking at that technical information you see that HDMI 2.0 can&#39;t do valve&#39;s claimed 4k@120Hz, this is because Linux doesn&#39;t have open-source drivers for HDMI 2.1 making them lose out on the naming, and likely some features, that being said Valve is still working to make sure it can do 4k@120Hz, HDR, FreeSync, and CEC. Ok now that I&#39;m 428 words into this paragraph let&#39;s get on to the important specs of the computer. The CPU is a Semi-custom AMD Zen 4 6C / 12T, up to 4.8 GHz, 30W TDP, this is a lot of info that many may not understand so I&#39;ll try to break it down to the best of my knowledge. Semi-custom likely just means they aren&#39;t using a standard chip and have it tuned for their use case, Zen 4 is the architecture and with it being last generation it&#39;s still plenty good for the low-medium gaming they advertise, 6 cores and 12 threads is also plenty good for their target gaming. 4.8 GHz is just the speed at which the CPU runs with bigger number equaling better. and 30W TDP is the power it uses, this is one of the more important stats to see for how fast the CPU will be and also for how it&#39;ll drain your electricity bill, 30W isn&#39;t a whole lot which is nice for the built in power supply and your wallet but not great for the performance though once again it should be perfectly fine. The most important spec is next, the GPU is a Semi-Custom AMD RDNA3 28CUs, 2.45GHz max sustained clock, 110W TDP, they are equating this to a 7600XT which I don&#39;t really see it but I&#39;m not great with nitty gritty details for GPUs all I see is the clock speed being very similar but the 7600XT has more CUs (Compute Units) and a higher TDP. Overall this comes down to one important stat VRAM which is the GPUs high speed RAM, this is not that good only being 8GB which over the years we are seeing become less and less ideal, while certainly is good enough for the target gaming profile it may not stay that way. Speaking from personal experience on a mobile 1650 with only 4GB VRAM it was good enough for low settings up until 2-3 years ago where I stopped being able to play the latest games at 60fps and now I can barely get the games to run at 30. So I&#39;m sure Valve&#39;s 8GB will be fine for now but in 5+ years it may not be so great. As for the system RAM it defaults at 16gb of DDR5 sodimm ram meaning you can open up your system and replace the ram like you would with a laptop, this is a very nice feature to have so you aren&#39;t stuck at 16 and could upgrade to 32 or more, they state it directly on the site how high it can go but if I were to guess it&#39;d be at least 64GB and probably higher. Storage will have two options a 512GB an a 2TB model both having the ability to add more with either a 2230 or a 2280 NVMe SSD. For connectivity it comes with 2x2 Wi-Fi 6E, Bluetooth 5.3, and an Integrated 2.4GHz Steam Controller wireless adapter allowing for native connection on the Steam Machine like that of a console. Overall after 938 words it&#39;s fair to say this is my most anticipated item pricing is a bit sketchy though we haven&#39;t gotten exact word but they stated that it would not be competitive with consoles and would instead be competitive with PCs, so what does this mean. No the Steam Machine will not be $400-500 my estimates would be $600 on the very very low side but closer to a $700-900 price range. I believe among many other people the price will determine the success of the Steam Machine but based on how low the specs really are I have my hopes up that it will be a lower more accessible price as I would like this to be the shift in the market to push Linux to the consumer space. The last thing I want to talk about with the Steam Machine is the front, it has a built in LED light bar that is configurable and a face plate that is replaceable with them offering the files to make your own face plate as you wish, I&#39;m a huge fan of customization and personalizing your hardware to your liking so this is a massive win for me. To conclude this paragraph the Steam Machine is a promising low-medium graphics gaming device that could push it&#39;s way into the console gaming space and truly make a difference if it&#39;s priced right, but for now it&#39;s too early to say. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Steam Frame is Valve&#39;s next entry into the VR space this time with a standalone headset with some ever more impressive features than the Valve Index. The Frame is an Android based standalone VR headset like the Meta Quest line of headsets. It has standard inside-out tracking so no base stations needed using many of the same technologies popularized by the Meta Quest. It&#39;s controllers . . . well they look extremely similar to the Quest controllers minus one major difference. They have a full set of face buttons and bumpers like that of a standard ABXY controller, this is something that as far as I know we haven&#39;t really seen in VR devices. This is because Valve is intending this to be able to be used for standard 2D games as well. Which then begs the question, how are they intending to have windows games play on an android system? This one has me excited, just like with SteamOS they are running a new layer of Proton this time to make games compatible with ARM chips allowing windows games to play natively on the device with no streaming needed. Despite this though they are also letting you stream from your PC to the headset too this time with a technology we haven&#39;t seen, foveated streaming. Similar to foveated rendering it uses eye tracking to see where you are looking but unlike foveated rendering this isn&#39;t lowering resolution around your vision instead it is adjusting the encoding to be focused around where you are looking letting them stream the game at the expected 2160 x 2160 72-144Hz gameplay to your headset at 10x the efficiency, and on top of this they are adding an additional optimization in the form of a wireless adapter connecting your Frame to your PC over a dedicated 6GHz Wi-Fi signal meaning your bandwidth won&#39;t be affected by other devices. This in theory should all allow for extremely high quality, low latency VR game streaming with little to no hiccups and according to reviewers it seems to be true. In LTT&#39;s video they mentioned how even about 50ft away, with no walls in the way mind you, it was like that of a direct PC connection, but on that no walls comment I made, while 6GHz is great for speed it&#39;s penetration is not that good so even just one wall in the way could affect your quality, overall this technology is extremely impressive and I&#39;m excited to hear more about it once reviewers can get their hands on it for real. Now onto specs, the Frame will have a 4nm Snapdragon® 8 Gen 3 running the ARM64 architecture at it&#39;s core, this I ultimately don&#39;t really understand as I am not familiar with mobile processors like snapdragon so I am unable to speak on personal knowledge but after a little research it seems to be a very capable processor and should offer some great performance and according to GadgetVersus who I do not know the reputability of it should offer better performance than the Quest 3&#39;s processor. It will also have 16GB of LPDDR5X RAM, and two storage options, 256GB and 1TB so while the storage is not upgradeable there you can still use a microSD card once again allowing you to transfer your games from your Steam Deck to your Steam Machine to your Steam Frame, giving you the ability to carry your games to all devices no downloads necessary. Valve is also calling this headset &#34;modular&#34; and in a sense it is, the headset and the headstrap are separate pieces and offer there own things with the Frame the headstrap isn&#39;t just a mount but it also holds the battery in the back allowing for better weight distribution but also can be charged from the back removing the annoying cable hazard from having your charger hang down around your arms requiring you to manage it behind you, along with the battery the headstrap also includes the audio drivers so while I heard complaints about the audio it&#39;s possible you could get an Index styled solution as just a separate headstrap. As mentioned earlier the displays are 2160 x 2160 LCD per eye at 72-144Hz though they do mention that the 144Hz is experimental all of this in compact pancake lenses with a large 110 FOV. They also mentioned possibly offering prescription lenses which would be a very welcome addition. The inside-out camera tracking uses 4 outward monochrome cameras for the controller and the headset tracking, and 2 interior cameras for eye tracking and foveated streaming. They also intend to allow monochrome passthrough and include IR illuminators for low-light tracking, in addition to this they are adding something new a user accessible front expansion port with a &#34;dual high speed camera interface (8 lanes @ 2.5Gbps MIPI) / PCIe Gen 4 interface (1-lane)&#34; while I&#39;m not sure what all can be done with this I can already imagine at least some features like face tracking, this is a unique addition that I could see offering some really cool modularity that we haven&#39;t seen before. For connectivity there are many many different radios, a Wi-Fi 7, 2x2, with dual radios enabling both a 5GHz Wi-Fi connection for online gaming and downloads, and a 6GHz connection dedicated for foveated streaming. Along with the Wi-Fi receivers there will be a Bluetooth 5.3 connections and a dedicated 2.4GHz link dedicated to for the Steam Frame Controllers. It&#39;s weight comes to an approximate 440g with both the core module and the headstrap combined and the core itself weighing 185g. Overall a really powerful standalone headset with a powerful wireless game streaming ability allowing you to play all of your games whether they be VR games or 2D games. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to conclude let&#39;s briefly give a TL:DR on all the new products. We are getting the Steam Controller which will have the Steam Deck&#39;s touchpads and 4 back buttons and new features like the next generation magnetic joysticks for improved accuracy along with capacitive grip sensors. Then there is the Steam Machine a mid tier gaming PC running Steams bespoke SteamOS all in a compact 6-inch cube. Last but far from least the Steam Frame a standalone VR headset with next generation wireless streaming technology that also runs SteamOS. This is a extremely powerful lineup and will likely cause a major shakeup in the gaming hardware industry. Prices haven&#39;t been specified but we can hope they will be decently accessible. Another hope that I have with the Steam Machine is that it will make a push for SteamOS to be used more and we can see a major competitor to go against windows, but this will all depend on the price of the Steam Machine when it comes out. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>